<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An answer to a printed letter to Dr. W.P. concerning non-resistance and other reasons for not taking the Oathes with some queries to the non-swearers in a postscript.</title>
            <author>Payne, William, 1650-1696.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 48 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A56735</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P895</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1141</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11875676</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11875676</idno>
            <idno type="VID">50220</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A56735)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 50220)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 504:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An answer to a printed letter to Dr. W.P. concerning non-resistance and other reasons for not taking the Oathes with some queries to the non-swearers in a postscript.</title>
                  <author>Payne, William, 1650-1696.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 38 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.R. for Brabazon Aylmer,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to William Payne.  Cf. Halkett &amp; Laing (2nd ed.)</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Revolution of 1688.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:50220:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:50220:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ANSWER To A <hi>Printed Letter</hi> TO Dr. W. P. Concerning NON-RESISTANCE, And other REASONS for not taking the OATHES.</p>
            <p>With ſome Queries to the Non-ſwearers in a <hi>POSTSCRIPT.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. R.</hi> for <hi>Brabazon Aylmer,</hi> at the <hi>Three Pigeons</hi> in <hi>Cornhil,</hi> over-againſt the <hi>Royal Exchange,</hi> 1690.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:50220:2"/>
            <p>Licenſed,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>September. 16. 1690.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:50220:2"/>
            <head>AN ANSWER To A <hi>Printed Letter</hi> TO Dr. W. P.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT was too great a Favour that you ſhould <hi>preſent</hi> me particularly <hi>with thoſe Reaſons which our diſſatisfied Clergy may have to offer for themſelves for their not taking the Oaths;</hi> when you were pleaſed to lay the chiefeſt ſtreſs of their not doing ſo upon the Doctrine of <hi>Non-Reſistance,</hi> that you ſhould ſingle me out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:50220:3"/>all my Brethren, who were as much Preachers of it as my ſelf, and put me upon the hard Task, as you thought no doubt, of reconciling <hi>that</hi> with the preſent Government and the preſent Oaths, or of renouncing the one or the other.</p>
            <p>The Pains which ſome of you have taken in the <hi>Hiſtory of Paſſive Obedience,</hi> ſhows that this is not the <hi>ſingular</hi> Doctrine of ſome few men but of <hi>Moſt</hi> if not <hi>All</hi> Divines, ſo that if it were a miſtake, and a man had bin i'the wrong, he has a great deal of good Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny with him, and need not be much aſhamed of being call'd out to do Penance alone, or be taken to task for ſuch a <hi>General</hi> Error. But however ſome of late are pleaſed to be very Angry or very Pleaſant with the Doctrine of <hi>Paſſive Obedience and Non-Reſiſtance,</hi> Rediculing and Expoſing it as the <hi>flattering Hereſie</hi> of the late Clergy, and talking againſt it at ſuch a rate as if they would have St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s words quite blotted out of the Bible, <hi>They that reſiſt ſhall receive to themſelves damnation;</hi> and when they are Friends to the preſent Government, yet do ſo far diſcredit it, as to be of their mind
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:50220:3"/>to think it inconſiſtent with <hi>that Principle,</hi> yet I am perfectly of another Opinion, and think <hi>that</hi> as true a Doctrine now as it was in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s time; and that we are no way bound to recant it in order to our taking the Oaths, and joyning with the preſent Government, or that it is neceſſary to give up either the <hi>one</hi> or the <hi>other.</hi> That this is a Chriſtian Doctrine in the general, as much as not <hi>Revenging</hi> or not <hi>Killing,</hi> St. <hi>Pauls</hi> words ſet it beyond all diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute, though there may be <hi>Limitations</hi> and <hi>Exceptions</hi> to them all in extraordinary Caſes, and it requires great Prudence and Caution when we come to the particular ſtating of this, and run into nice Diſcourſes about Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which many a good Divine may no more underſtand than Matters of Trade; and therefore may be apt to miſtake in ſome <hi>Caſes</hi> of both, and commit great overſights in going out of his Province, and applying general Rules to ſome particular Caſes that will not bear them. The way of rightly ſtating this Doctrine, I have always thought was accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the <hi>Form</hi> and <hi>Conſtitution</hi> of our Laws and Government; whatever <hi>they</hi> are we are to be paſſive to them, and ought not to reſiſt
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:50220:4"/>that <hi>Legal Power</hi> and <hi>Conſtitution</hi> which is the <hi>Ordinance of God</hi> which he has ſet over us.</p>
            <p>But to make it an Inſtrument to deſtroy our Laws and our Conſtitution by advancing Prerogative above Law, and ſetting up I know not what <hi>Imperial</hi> Power above the <hi>Political,</hi> and requiring ſuch a <hi>Loyalty</hi> to the Prince in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, as is no way due by the Law of the Land, which is the true Rule and Meaſure of our Duty, this is to ſtate it wrong, and to ſqueeze and wring a great Error and Miſcheif out of a Real Truth; and whether this hath not bin done by a great many who have there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by brought an Odium and Diſcredit upon the Doctrine it ſelf, I leave you to judge; but there is not the leaſt colour of charging this upon any of my Sermons, where I lay the matter very much upon our own Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and allow expreſly the other <hi>Proviſion</hi> in the <hi>German</hi> Empire, and in the <hi>Capitulation</hi> of <hi>Spain</hi> and the <hi>Low Countries, pag.</hi> 25. <hi>Serm.</hi> 2. But if <hi>the Unlawfulneſs of Reſiſting upon any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence whatſoever,</hi> was a <hi>ſlaviſh Doctrine</hi> in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> as ſome inconſidering Men throw out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Clergy, 'twas more owing to the two Houſes of Parliament who made <hi>that</hi> a Legal
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:50220:4"/>Declaration, then to any of the Clergy who Preached it up.</p>
            <p>I doubt not but <hi>that,</hi> as general and abſolute as it was, carried in it the <hi>Suppoſition</hi> of the <hi>Legal Conſtitution,</hi> and was not deſigned to alter or overthrow <hi>that,</hi> but there may ſome extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Caſes happen which no poſitive Laws can provide againſt, or ought indeed to ſuppoſe, but when they do happen the plain Reaſon and Neceſſity of things will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide againſt them, and there cannot be certain and ſtanding Rules made for them, but they fall under the <hi>Equity</hi> and <hi>Reaſon</hi> though not the <hi>Letter</hi> of the Conſtitution. I am fully of the mind that it is more for Publick Good and the Peace of the World, to teach People the Doctrines of Obedience to Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, and Non-Reſiſtance Generally and Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely, then to open a <hi>door</hi> to unquiet Spirits to diſturb the Government they live under up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all occaſions, but yet the greateſt Divines who have Conſcientiouſly done this, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly Dr. <hi>Falkner</hi> among our own, when they have bin unwilling to allow any particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar and practical Caſes of doing otherwiſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they do but ſeldom and extraordinarily
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:50220:5"/>fall out, yet when they do, muſt and cannot but allow an exception to a general Duty, as he particularly mentions the caſe of <hi>Antio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus,</hi> and <hi>of a Princes deſign to deſtroy and ruin a conſiderable part of his People contrary to the eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh'd Laws;</hi> to which ſome think ours comes up under King <hi>James,</hi> and yet he ſtill vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates that General Declaration <hi>of not Reſiſting upon any pretence whatſoever,</hi> becauſe that is ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily and generally true, and the exception to it is ſo rare and extraordinary as ought not to be taken in and ſuppoſed; and as no way hinders the Truth of ſuch a general ſaying, as when holy Scripture declare that <hi>Wives and Children muſt obey their Husbands and Parents</hi> in all things; and <hi>whom God hath joyned together no man muſt put aſunder.</hi> Theſe Declarations how general ſoever, and how Excluſive they may ſeem of doing otherwiſe <hi>upon any pretence what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever,</hi> yet ſtill are not without ſome Excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in extraordinary Caſes, which all Divines do allow.</p>
            <p>Some Caſes may fall out in Government, though they ought not to be ſuppoſed, nor can well be provided againſt: As if a King
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:50220:5"/>ſhall endeavor to deſtroy his People, to change the Conſtitution, to turn a Legal Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment into an Abſolute Empire; if he ſhall put a ſtop to Juſtice, and ſhut up <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall,</hi> and give out no Commiſſions to Judges and Sheriffs, and appoint either none or other Officers then the Law knows; if he ſhall fall into Lunacy and Madneſs, or the like incapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city, if he ſhall voluntarily Deſert and Leave the Kingdom without any Government; if the whole Royal Family ſhall be extinct, and there be no Lineal Heirs to the Crown; if the right Heir be dubious, or there be a reaſonable ground to believe a ſuppoſitious Child put in the place of the right Heir: In theſe, and ſuch like Caſes there is no ordinary Proviſion made by our Law, nor indeed can there well or poſſibly be in all of them; but when they do happen, the plain Neceſſity and Reaſon of the thing muſt direct to ſome proviſion or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and it is very unreaſonable to quarrel with that becauſe it is not in every thing agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able with ordinary and ſtanding Rules, and the exact Meaſures that the Laws do at other times require, but cannot then be obſerved.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:50220:6"/>
            <p> This Sir anſwers all that is objected in the latter part of your Letter, which is the moſt conſiderable thing in it, <hi>concerning the Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Houſe of Commons, whither they had as you ſay, any Authority to Act as an Houſe of Parliament in impoſing theſe Oaths? pag.</hi> 4. <hi>Let.</hi> Becauſe,
<q>
                  <list>
                     <item>Firſt, Our Law owns no Parliaments but what are called by the Kings Writs.</item>
                     <item>Secondly, Nor doth it know any Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the lower Houſe, but who are cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen for a Parliament.</item>
                     <item>Thirdly, Nor doth it give right to any to Act in the Houſe till they have taken the Teſt.</item>
                     <item>Fourthly, And if any one enter and take their place there, before they have taken the Oath of Supremacy, their Place is void, and they are not at Liberty to take it after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, new Election is to be made; 5 <hi>Eliz. cap.</hi> 1.</item>
                     <item>Fifthly and Laſtly, The former Oaths of Allegiance and Supremacy have bin ſo impoſed by divers Statutes, and are ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly required of all Members of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that none could poſſibly have a power
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:50220:6"/>of Subſtituting others in their ſtead till they had taken thoſe and had ſwore, if not that they believed King <hi>James,</hi> yet at leaſt that they believed King <hi>William</hi> to be right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful King of this Land.</item>
                  </list>
               </q> 
               <hi>i. e.</hi> The Members of Parliament were before their Sitting to take the Oaths of Allegiance and Supremacy to the King.</p>
            <p>Now becauſe this is true in all ordinary Caſes muſt it be ſo in all extraordinary ones too? Were all theſe things obſerved by the Convention in 1660 which brought in King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second? And are we therefore to be diſſatisfied about the Laws they made, and the proceedings done by them, becauſe ſome of you <hi>may think that by our Conſtitution, a Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hath no power at all in Law?</hi> And becauſe they obſerved not all the ordinary Rules required at other times by our Laws? If we do, we ſhall call in queſtion the <hi>Legality</hi> at leaſt of that Revolution, and that Convention as well as of this.</p>
            <p>The Truth is, Poſitive Laws cannot al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways be obſerved, but muſt give way to the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:50220:7"/>greater Law of Neceſſity, and of notorious greater good; and even the Laws of God himſelf have often done ſo, as we find in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture. When therefore you urge on your ſide ſome particular Laws of the Kingdom which you cannot wholly reconcile with the preſent Government, and this I believe is the great Difficulty that ſticks with you; we on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide think it ſuch an extraordinary Caſe as diſpenſes with thoſe, and that the plainneſs and notoriety of the thing may ſatisfie any mans Conſcience about it, and did ſo when the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> came, even theſe who now diſſent, not only wiſht well to the Prince, and went over to him in their Hearts and Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but denied their Aſſiſtance to King <hi>James;</hi> and did ſeveral other things which the Law would not warrant them in had it not bin an extraordinary Caſe; and moſt if not all of you have to my knowledge own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed you did go in with the Prince ſo far as his Declaration, which was not altogether ſtrictly Legal I ſuppoſe, by any of our Laws in bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a King by ſuch a manner to good Terms, ſo that we muſt leave God to judge whither it was not in the whole, ſuch an extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:50220:7"/>and extralegal Caſe as juſtifies whatever was done though not altogether according to expreſs Laws and whither we have not acted ſincerely in thinking ſo all along, and you unreaſonably and perverſly in thinking other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe at one time, though not at another.</p>
            <p>As to what you urge out of the Statute of 1. <hi>James</hi> 1. which declares <hi>the Right to the Monarchy to have lineally deſcended to the Prince, and by Proximity of Blood, and that hereupon he was recognized and ſubmitted to by the whole Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and not upon any Choice or Election of the People.</hi> Who will not own this to be a common and rightful way of coming to the Crown in ſuch an Hereditary Monarchy as ours is? But does that Statute ſay, that no other King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> who-ever came to the Crown, or ever ſhould without ſuch a Lineal Deſcent and Proximity of Bloud, was rightful King? Or does it ſay that King and Parliament have not a power to limit and ſettle the deſcent of the Crown according to the Thirteenth of <hi>Elizabeth?</hi> Does it take away that Act by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs Words, without which I think our Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers ſay no former Act is nulled or abrogated? What is it then to the purpoſe? Have not
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:50220:8"/>King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary</hi> a right of Blood and Lineal Deſcent, if King <hi>James</hi> his Right be ceaſed? Do they or the Kingdom ever own or declare that they hold the Crown by the Choice or Election of the People? Have not half of the Kings of <hi>England,</hi> before the Conqueſt and after, bin as much or more cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen by the people according to all our Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians? Is there not a great difference between the Peoples Chooſing and Electing of a King, and the States and Repreſentatives of a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom Recognizing and Declaring them to be King and Queen by whatever unnamed Right? When you have ſatisfied me in theſe Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons you will fully ſatisfie your ſelf about that Matter.</p>
            <p>You tell me there is another Statute of the ſame King, that <hi>enjoyns the Oath of Allegiance to him, as the true and Rightful King, and (which deſerves well to be conſidered) makes it Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to go about to perſwade one to take the Oath to any elſe.</hi> Now is it any wonder or does it deſerve any mighty Conſideration, that the Law ſhould make it Treaſon to go about to perſwade one to take the Oath of Allegiance to him that is not King, this ſure if any thing tends to the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:50220:8"/>Kings Diſheriſon and Deſtruction; and <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> I ſuppoſe, and ſome of the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Party in the beginning of King <hi>James</hi> I. Reign had ſuch a deſign againſt which that Statute is levelled; but that which you bring it for, is upon the account of the <hi>Rightful</hi> King, ſo that you would have it meant againſt thoſe who are for a King <hi>de facto</hi> only that is not <hi>Rightful:</hi> Now though this does not in the leaſt concern me, but thoſe who are of that Opinion, to anſwer, yet I believe this Statute had no Eye to any ſuch thing nor is any way concerned about it, nor does it however take away the Act of <hi>Henry the Seventh</hi> about thoſe who adhere to the King in Poſſeſſion, but what you add to it is very Conſiderable, and the greateſt though ſhorteſt thing in your whole Letter (for as to the buſineſs of Non-Reſiſtance, I take that to be very impertinent to the Clergy's taking the Oaths, and to concern only a very few others) which is this; <hi>So long as Allegiance is thus due to the Rightful King, you would be very kind if you would ſhew thoſe that are diſſatisfied, that they may transfer it to any other without Sin.</hi> Now, Sir, in anſwer to this, I muſt own that I know not how Allegiance can be due to two Kings at
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:50220:9"/>once; to a King <hi>de jure</hi> and a King <hi>de facto,</hi> no one can actually ſerve two ſuch Maſters, but if our Law allow ſuch a diſtinction, which I am not at preſent to diſpute, then it muſt by requiring Allegiance to the King <hi>de facto,</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge us at that time from the Allegiance due to the King <hi>de jure,</hi> and transfer it to the other; if there be ſuch a Law and Conſtitution of the Kingdom for the ſake of Publick Peace and the ſecurity of private Perſons, I would know what Law of God there is againſt it? And then whether a Man may not without ſin ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to it, and take the benefit of it? But I think Allegiance to a Rightful King ceaſes, by his ceaſing to be King; and then it may be eaſily known know it comes to be transfer'd to another.</p>
            <p>As to the 12 <hi>Carol.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 30. <hi>That neither the Peers of this Land, nor the Commons, nor both together in Parliament or out of Parliament, nor the People Collectively or Repreſentatively, nor any other perſons whatſoever, have any Coercive power over the Perſons of the Kings of this Realm.</hi> This will be readily owned, you know, by me who do not think that <hi>our Government is ſuch as that of the</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:50220:9"/>Lacedemonians <hi>under their Kings and Ephori,</hi> and by all but thoſe who are of the mind of the Judges of <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt; had thoſe who were chiefly concerned in the late revolution bin of another Opinion, K. <hi>James</hi> had bin ſtopt from going either to <hi>France</hi> or to <hi>Ireland.</hi> Our Peers and Commons in Parliament did not uſe any Coercive power over King <hi>James,</hi> nor give any proper judicial Sentence againſt him to exclude him the Government, as having any Superiority or Sovereignty over him, but only declared the throne Vacant of him for many Reaſons, and that <hi>William</hi> and <hi>Mary</hi> were King and Queen of this Realm, and this they did, not as formal Judges but as Arbitrators made ſo by the neceſſity of the Circumſtances we were then in, and however you may diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like their award and Arbitrement, for which they alone are anſwerable, yet if as private Perſons you may not ſubmit to it, you muſt break up the World, and disband the Society of Mankind, and neceſſarily run into a ſtate of War and Confuſion, and we ſhall be hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly able to live under any Government what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever. However you do not think I ſuppoſe that a Foreign Prince is tyed up and obliged
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:50220:10"/>by that Statute againſt making War upon a King of <hi>England</hi> when he ſuppoſes him to have done him an otherwiſe irreparable injury, nor are the Nation hindered hereby from go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing over to the juſt ſide or bound to aſſiſt their Prince in an unjuſt Cauſe, eſpecially when they know it would have bin to their own cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Deſtruction.</p>
            <p>Thus I think the <hi>Matter</hi> might be <hi>ſtated</hi> without touching upon any of thoſe Statutes you mention or the Doctrine of <hi>Non-Reſiſtance</hi> and Paſſive Obedience which lye far enough out of the way from hindering our taking the Oathes or coming into the Government, though you think fit to throw them in as Rubs to keep you from both; but you deſire me <hi>not to ſhift of the matter to a Conqueſt, which is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther owned by King nor People,</hi> and yet may be true enough in point of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> though not inſiſted on in point of <hi>Prudence; Nor to a Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cancy by a voluntary Deſertion, which is a falſity in matter of Fact;</hi> and yet if it be well conſidered it will amount to as much as if he had bin brought to a Reſignation under his hand, and may as well ſatisfie any Mans Conſcience,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:50220:10"/>for that might with as much reaſon be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to be as little Voluntary, <hi>and not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a deſign of returning to his Government again, if he could;</hi> but this I dare aſſure you is true in matter of Fact that King <hi>James</hi> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther choſe to go away, than to tarry and call a Parliament, and give thereby a reaſonable Security to the Nation againſt Popery and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction; and this was not only <hi>Voluntary</hi> but <hi>Deliberate</hi> too, and upon the Advice of his Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Counſellors, and ſo far it was a <hi>Voluntary Deſertion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to the Caſe of <hi>Non-Reſiſtance,</hi> what I have ever <hi>taught from the Preſs or the Pulpit,</hi> in neither of which <hi>Chair</hi> I pretend to be Infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, or have in a ſolemn manner profeſſed that <hi>it is not lawful upon any pretence whatſoever to take up arms againſt the King or any Commiſſioned by him,</hi> I did it <hi>as you hope,</hi> and God is my Witneſs, <hi>in the ſincerity of my heart,</hi> for the good of the World and Peace of Mankind, as I thought it agreeable to the Law of God, and the Law of the Land, and I do not think that either this or any other Wiſe Government, will think it a dangerous Opinion, or oblige any Divine to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:50220:11"/>Renounce or Recant it, and if any unſeen and extraordinary Caſe ſhould ever happen to be an exception againſt it, I am clearly of the mind 'tis much better to let it alone to provide for it ſelf when it comes, then to mention it in a Sermon or Practical Diſcourſe, and fill Peoples Heads with a Nicety they may be too apt to abuſe. As to give you a plain Caſe, if you were to Preach againſt Stealing, and taking away another mans Goods without his conſent, and were ſhowing the great Miſchief and Unlawfulneſs of it in all Caſes, and how contrary it was both to the good of the World, and to the Laws of God and of Man, you would not, I ſuppoſe, think it Neceſſary or Prudent to acquaint your Auditory with that extraordinary Caſe of a Mans Stealing for the ſupport of his Life, when he muſt otherwiſe ſtarve, though you with <hi>Thomas Aquinas,</hi> and other Divines, thought it lawful to do ſo in ſuch a Caſe of Neceſſity.</p>
            <p>The Caſe of <hi>Non-Reſiſtance,</hi> however high it was carried in all the likely and practical Caſes, to ſtop moſt of the Holes at which Treaſon and Rebellion might be then apt to break out, or at leaſt through which Factious
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:50220:11"/>Spirits might as they pleaſed creep out of that ordinary Duty and Obedience they owed to the Government and have too many others to follow them, and ſo embroil and diſturb the World, <hi>by diſobeying and reſiſting as they thought fit,</hi> ſo that if we would ſpeak to any purpoſe it was neceſſary to ſpeak to thoſe Caſes and to ſhow the unlawfulneſs of private Perſons Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting or Rebelling either in <hi>the Caſe of meer Religion,</hi> or <hi>the Caſe of Legal Rights,</hi> when we might juſtly complain with the Primitive Chriſtians in <hi>Tertullians</hi> Apology that ſome of thoſe were taken from us and yet ſtill ſuffer patiently; or in <hi>the Caſe of Natural Defence</hi> which is not ſo allowable to private Perſons againſt the Government as againſt one another, and <hi>the Otherwiſe Remedileſs Caſe by the encroachment of Princes,</hi> who are not to be Reſiſted for every encroachment. But in all theſe Caſes there may be ſeveral degrees which you do not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, and which it was not ſo proper for me to do at that time. However in all of them there is not that great, but one would think unlikely, and therefore unthought of Caſe, of a Princes Deſtroying the Community, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verturning the Government, and Ruining the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:50220:12"/>greateſt part of his People; concerning which I deſire you to conſult Dr. <hi>Falkner,</hi> and ſee what he ſays about it, who has yet ſpoken as fully for <hi>Non-Reſiſtance</hi> in all Caſes as I or you your ſelf can do; and I think now you find that true which you quote out of my Sermon, and which might have deſerved another ſort of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark from you, though it was ſpoke without the Spirit of Prophecy, namely, <hi>That Gods Providence and Government of the World is the beſt Security in this and all other Evils we are ſubject to;</hi> that <hi>the great Patron of Juſtice will ſet bounds to the Power and Injustice of Princes; and as far as is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for the good of the World, and for his wiſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, ſo far they ſhall go and no farther;</hi> that <hi>he will take the matter into his own hands, &amp; ſatis eſt quod Deum expectent ultorem,</hi> who will not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſtrike them immediately and miraculouſly with Thunder from Heaven, but raiſe up In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments, and find out means in his Wiſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence to Deliver a people by thoſe who were under no manner of Obligation from the Doctrine of <hi>Non-Reſiſtance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Clergy who have taken the Oathes, were no more concerned in Reſiſting K. <hi>James</hi> while he was their King, nor <hi>in adhereing to any</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:50220:12"/>that did ſo <hi>in this particular,</hi> than any of you who refuſe the Oaths, and for that ſin of Omiſſion in not Aſſiſting him, which is a duty we are ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily bound to by our Laws and by our for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Oaths, <hi>that</hi> if it be one, is a common Crime we are both equally reſponſible for, and the ſame reaſon by which you <hi>unlooſe your ſelves</hi> from part of the Oath of Allegiance, which was to defend and aſſiſt the King, and which made you <hi>not think your ſelves bound to keep that</hi> when the Prince came becauſe it tended to your manifeſt deſtruction, might have unlooſed you from the whole, even, if you pleaſe <hi>as Sampſon did his withs;</hi> and we think our ſelves now fully un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>looſed by his not being King.</p>
            <p>I wonder therefore, and can hardly think you in earneſt, when you bring ſuch frivolous and unconcluding Reaſons for your not taking the Oaths, or non-compliance with the preſent Government, which can ſatisfie no body; and if they expoſe any, 'tis thoſe who bring them, as for example, <hi>becauſe ye would not be like a kind of Weather-glaſſes, by having your obedience to Governors higher or lower according to the temperature or variati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of outward Affairs.</hi> This fancy of Weather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glaſſes has had great Honour and Credit done to it by ſeveral of your party, and particularly
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:50220:13"/>by the Wiſe Publiſher of the <hi>Hiſtory of Paſſive Obedience,</hi> who was pleaſed to put it into his <hi>Preface</hi> as the only piece of Wit there, and if any of you ſtand in the ſame need of it, and it be further ſerviceable to you, the Owner of it will ſtill allow you the free uſe of it, but then pray take this with it, and all that belongs to it, <hi>That none may be ſo malicious as to think we Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culate our Sermons meerly for the preſent Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, as if the Pulpit were a kind of Weather-glaſs wherein the Doctrine of Obedience to Governours is higher or lower according to the Temperature or Vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of outward Affairs,</hi> I challenge Malice it ſelf to name the Pulpit where this Doctrine has faln ſo much as half a tenth ſince the late Revolution, or where the contrary Doctrine, to wit, the Lawfulneſs of Reſiſting has ever bin Preach'd by any unleſs perhaps by a Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwearer; ſo that I ſee no danger hereby of <hi>our rendering our Miniſterial endeavors uſeleſs and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>effectual,</hi> or <hi>becoming a great Scandal and Diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance to ſuch as have known our former Doctrine and manner of Life and bringing a reproach upon the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Religion we profeſs.</hi> If any thing of this be, it is owing more to thoſe who ſtand out, who thereby furniſh ſome weak Perſons with <hi>Scruples,</hi> and ſome diſcontented ones with <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:50220:13"/>againſt the preſent Government, but which of us <hi>do hereby render their Miniſterial endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vors more uſeleſs and ineffectual,</hi> let the Body of the Nation judge, and let any of your ſelves judge by the ſmall number of thoſe whom you can bring to be of your Minds in your own Pariſhes; if you come to conſider Conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as ye thus object to us upon our coming in to the Government, what are thoſe upon your ſtanding out, but the Ruin not only of your Country, but of the <hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi> here, and all over <hi>Europe;</hi> and the ſerving a Cauſe, and joyning in an Intereſt that no Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt <hi>Engliſhman</hi> or Hearty <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> though he may ſuffer for it in Conſcience, yet can in Conſcience wiſh well to; you need therefore be as Cautious againſt thoſe, as <hi>you are</hi> you ſay, <hi>againſt Treaſon, becauſe you have bin told,</hi> and I hope you would have bin ſo, if you had not bin told, <hi>that Treaſon has ſtood ſo long in this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> in the late times, <hi>that it has run to ſeed, and ſcattered its principles, &amp;c.</hi> and <hi>that it is a Diſeaſe, which though it be not like the Sweating Sickneſs of old, a Malady peculiar to</hi> Engliſhmen, <hi>yet the plenty and luxury of our Country may perhaps make us more ſubject to it than others;</hi> I would therefore have your Party have a care of it, for I do not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:50220:14"/>this Government will be more a friend to it than any other, but I think no man is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by a thouſand ſuch like Quotations ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther againſt Treaſon or for <hi>Non-Reſiſtance,</hi> which will hold as long as there is any Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment i'the World; and I am of Opinion that Treaſon is as great a Crime under K. <hi>William</hi>'s Reign, and <hi>Non-Reſistance</hi> as much a Duty as it was under K. <hi>Charles</hi>'s.</p>
            <p>I can eaſily grant you all that either I or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers have ſaid much better upon that Subject, while they have kept to the Laws and to the Conſtitution, and not run into ſuch Notions and Schemes of Government as deſtroy both, and nothing will follow or be concluded from it that ſhall in the leaſt injure K. <hi>William,</hi> if he be our true and proper Sovereign, or be any way ſerviceable to K. <hi>James,</hi> if he be not. This is the great Point which you have not hit, but may if you pleaſe make it the Subject of the next loving Letter between us: All that is in this I have anſwered with that kindneſs and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penneſs that becomes a Friend, and <hi>with that ſeriouſneſs</hi> that becomes a point of Conſcience and ſuch as I fear not <hi>to be aſhamed of at the laſt day.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>And I am ſtill, <salute>Sir,</salute> 
               <signed>
                  <hi>Yours and</hi> Non-Reſiſtances Faithful Friend and Humble Servant, <hi>W. P.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:50220:14"/>
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>SInce the Writing, but before I had the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity of ſending this to you, a few <hi>Scrupulous Quaeries</hi> came into my Thoughts, which ſeem to me to have more weight in them to incline a Conſcientious Man to take the Oaths, and come in to the Government, then the Doctrine of <hi>Paſſive Obedience and Non-Reſiſtance</hi> can have to keep him out and make him forbear; and therefore with the ſame Freedom and Civility you have uſed to me in deſiring an Anſwer to thoſe Scruples on the one ſide, I beg the favour of you to give a fair and plain Reſolution of the other.</p>
            <p>Firſt then, I would ask whether it be, or were, <hi>a full judgment and perſwaſion of the down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right Sinfulneſs and Unlawfulneſs of taking the Oathes, or only ſome doubts and ſcruples and diſſatisfaction in your Minds about it that does or did hinder you?</hi> I have reaſon to think it is or was only the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, becauſe ſeveral of you have expreſly own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed this, and have therefore judged more cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritably of your Brethren than to believe ſo
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:50220:15"/>many ventured upon an action that carried a downright Sinfulneſs and Unlawfulneſs in it; but if others could ſatisfie themſelves about it, and could do it, you thought they might, and did no way blame or condemn them for it. This I am ſure was the judgment and the words too of many of you, <hi>nay the beſt and greateſt of your Diſſenting Brethren did not ſay any thing to their Friends or ſo much as admoniſh their young Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lains, and others who were under their immediate care,</hi> againſt taking the Oathes, when they knew they were inclined and diſpoſed ſo to do. Now if they inſtead of ſome leſſer doubts and private ſcruples had made a full judgment about the Sinfulneſs and Unlawfulneſs of this, how could they be excuſed for thus <hi>ſuffering ſin upon</hi> others who were under their Charge, and not giving warning as <hi>Watchmen</hi> to thoſe who belonged to their inſpection? <hi>who dwelt in your houſes, and were within your gates?</hi> whoſe Souls they were to take care of, leſt <hi>their bloud ſhould be required at their hands,</hi> and their Sin ſhould be charged upon their neglect. <hi>Nay, how could any of the Biſhops ſatisfie themſelves in not doing this to their whole Dioceſſes, and immediate Cures,</hi> whatever Worldly Perils and Inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niencies
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:50220:15"/>they had hereby ran, that ſo at leaſt <hi>they might have delivered their own Souls?</hi> I take it therefore for granted that it was not a full judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and perſwaſion of the downright Sinful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Unlawfulneſs of taking the Oaths, but only ſome leſſer doubts and private ſcruples which hindered <hi>them,</hi> and many of you from ſo doing; if any of you have ſince come to a greater Plerophory, and your Convictions have riſen with your Reſentments, God and your own Conſciencies muſt judge of that; but whilſt ye were only under thoſe <hi>Doubts,</hi> and ſo thought it ſafer not to do the thing than do it, whilſt ye thus doubted about it, and had ſome Scru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples concerning it remaining in your Minds, I ask whether theſe doubts and ſcruples of yours ſhould not have bin over-ruled by the many Reaſons on the other ſide, by the great and evident Miſchiefs of your ſtanding out both to the Church and Kingdom, and the no leſs great good to the Proteſtant Religion both at home and abroad by this Revolution? And whether it were not or had not bin Lawful in this Caſe, <hi>to have Acted even with a Doubting Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience?</hi> I am ſure we have often told the other Diſſenters ſo in the Caſe of Church-Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:50220:16"/>and I queſtion not but it is a true Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple that a man may and often ought to act <hi>with a doubting Conſcience</hi> where there are only ſome ſcruples, and diſſatisfactions that he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not perfectly get rid off on one ſide, and ſuch great Reaſons as the Peace and Unity of the Church or Kingdom on the other, tho' never againſt an <hi>Erronious</hi> one where he has formed a full and complete tho' wrong judgment of the ſinfulneſs and unlawfulneſs of an Action; and here by the way I would recommend to you, to conſider over again and apply to your ſelves what ye have formerly ſaid and written againſt thoſe Diſſenters in the matter of <hi>Schiſme,</hi> and in the Matter of a <hi>Doubting Conſcience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, I Query, <hi>Whether moſt if not all of the Diſſenting Clergy were not once well ſatisfied in their Conſciences about the Prince of</hi> Orange<hi>'s com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing over, and rejoiced in it as their only Deliverance under God from their Ruin they ſaw coming upon the Church and Nation; when they wiſh'd well to him and pray'd for him, and went over to him with their Hearts and Affections, if not more overtly by Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes and other Applications. Why ſhould they then think themſelves now ſo indiſpenſably obliged to King</hi> James, <hi>and ſo inſeparably bound to him by their
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:50220:16"/>Oathes of Allegiance, which they then thought they were in great meaſure diſcharged and releaſed from?</hi> For who then thought himſelf bound in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience <hi>to defend King</hi> James <hi>in all his Rights, Priviledges and Preheminencies whatſoever,</hi> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Oath of Allegiance, and to aſſiſt him to the utmoſt of their power againſt one who ſeemed and was declared by him to be an open Enemy and Invader? What Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the Church of <hi>England</hi> encouraged the Souldiers to Fight againſt him, and did not rather declare it unlawful ſo to do when it was ſo plainly fighting againſt their Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and their Country, which were then thought ſufficient Conſiderations to ſuperſede an otherwiſe neceſſary Duty? I ask therefore whither the ſame reaſons which then ſatisfied us all, and which ye then thought releaſed you from part of your Oath of Allegiance, and from giving King <hi>James</hi> that Aſſiſtance which had bin otherwiſe due to him, had it not mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly tended to the utter Ruin of your ſelves and your Religion, and the whole Kingdom, may not as well and much better diſcharge you now from that Allegiance which ye pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend is ſtill owing to him, and why they who were for taking away his Authority and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſſing
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:50220:17"/>him of his Government by a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gency during his Life, and without his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent as the only expedient to ſecure the Church and Nation from Ruin under him, ſhould think they were under ſuch a ſtrict and unal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terable Obligation to him by their former Oaths, and the Laws of the Land? Whither thoſe were not more irreconcilable with ſuch a method than with a New King? Farther, Whether thoſe who ſate in the Convention, and in the Parliament too when it was made ſuch by the Authority of King <hi>William,</hi> till they went off upon the Act for taking the Oathes, did not own the preſent Government, and ſhake off that of King <hi>James?</hi> I would there-therefore beg leave to ask <hi>thoſe,</hi> and all of you why you did ſo many ways leave King <hi>James</hi> then, and adhere ſo cloſely to him now? Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ye have changed your Minds, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered your Opinions, and repent of the Zeal which moſt of you ſhowed for the Prince? Whether ye would not do the ſame things again ye did then if ye were in the ſame Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances? If ſo, if ye can alter your judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in ſo little a time, why ſhould ye ſo much wonder at others, and object it to them
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:50220:17"/>as an inſtance of their mutability and ſudden change of their Opinions in the Caſe of <hi>Non-Reſiſtance,</hi> and <hi>Paſſive Obedience,</hi> tho' ye have no reaſon for it, when ſo far as I ſee ye have as much Power over your own Minds, and have as ſuddenly changed your own Opinions, and acted, ſome of you, as inconſiſtently and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictorily to your ſelves, as ye ſuppoſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers have done.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, I would ask you, <hi>Whether ye can produce any Examples of Chriſtian Biſhops or Prieſts or any other Chriſtians ſince the times of our Saviour who ever ſuffered on ſuch an Account or for ſuch a Cauſe as ye now do? viz.</hi> for not ſubmitting to the Civil Government that was Eſtabliſht amongſt them, and owned and acknowledged by the States and Repreſentatives of a Kingdom, and for ſuch a <hi>Cauſe</hi> as thoſe who are honeſt and ſincere cannot heartily wiſh Succeſs to, or pray to God that it ſhould thrive and proſper; for we have a better Opinion of moſt of you than to believe ye would have King <hi>James</hi> Conquer King <hi>William</hi> with the <hi>French</hi> Fleet and <hi>Iriſh</hi> Army, and that it was as far from you as from us to deſire this a few Months ago, and that ye cannot in your Hearts wiſh that K. <hi>James</hi> ſhould
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:50220:18"/>come back again in his preſent circumſtances, unleſs ſo miraculouſly changed, and in ſuch a wonderful manner that we may almoſt as rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably hope that God ſhould raiſe his Father and ſend him to live again and reign over us. Bating then ſuch a Miracle as that, <hi>what would ye have?</hi> no Government, to which we ſhould pay Allegiance, and from which we ſhould expect Protection, but rather that all things ſhould run into <hi>Anarchy</hi> and Confuſion, as King <hi>James</hi> left them, till he ſhall pleaſe to return again? Alaſs a Kingdom cannot like a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man deſerted by her former Husband or Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorced from him, live ſingle and not Marry again, but muſt have ſome Government im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately, and ſome other Ruler beſides the Mob. When therefore in ſuch a Caſe a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment is ſetled in a way ye may not like, but cannot help, in the beſt and only way it could then be; for either the longeſt Sword or moſt Votes muſt carry it, (which were then both of a ſide) nay when it is eſtabliſht in a way moſt agreeable to our old Conſtitution, muſt private Perſons loſe all they have rather then come into it? They muſt leave the World, and live in very few Governments
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:50220:18"/>long if they do this: Did any of the Primitive Chriſtians do ſo who had as much reaſon to be diſſatisfied with ſeveral Governments they liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed under, and eſpecially to queſtion the Right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Title of many of their Supreme Governors as you can have? and yet never that I know of did they ſuffer on ſuch an account, much leſs for ſuch an <hi>untoward</hi> Cauſe as ye now do.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, I would ask you, <hi>If you believed the matter of Fact true that King</hi> James <hi>had put a ſuppoſitious Child upon the Kingdom to exclude the Right Heirs, and had made a League with</hi> France <hi>to overturn the Legal Government and Conſtitution, and had reſolved to uſe the utmoſt Force and violence to bring in Popery by</hi> French <hi>Dragooning, and</hi> Iriſh <hi>Maſſacring, and were endeavoring and likely to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh all this; whether in ſuch a caſe ye could think your ſelves diſcharged of your Allegiance to him and that ye were no longer bound to him as your Rightful King?</hi> If ye could, then ye muſt grant this Principle that a King may ceaſe to be King, and loſe his Right to your Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance without a Natural Death or voluntary Reſignation, and then you will have as much to anſwer for <hi>Paſſive Obedience</hi> and <hi>Non-Reſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance,</hi> as you think others now have; when you ſhall ſend me word that you will give me
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:50220:19"/>this Principle, and put the Iſſue upon the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Fact, I'le give you a further account of that. If you will not own this, but ſtill hold to indiſſoluble Allegiance, and <hi>Paſſive Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> let the King deſtroy all his People and all the Laws and Rights of the Kingdom, and the Inheritance of the Crown too, and that in ſuch a Notorious Caſe, his Right and your Allegiance ſtill continue in full force, then ye ſtand to ſuch Principles as will make Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment a great Curſe very often inſtead of a Bleſſing to Mankind, and ſuch a Yoke as nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we nor our <hi>Fathers</hi> were able to bear, who did in vain ſettle any Legal Rights and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh any Legal Conſtitution if their Poſterity are bound in Conſcience to let go their claim to all this, and give it all up, when a raſh and reſolute Prince will be contented with nothing leſs, than deſtroying the Government by which he is King; I cannot believe that any of you can ſoberly and in good earneſt believe ſuch a Principle or carry it ſo high but only as it is neceſſary for you to defend your ſelves and your Caſe at preſent, and though you are then driven as far as we can follow you, yet like the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> your Refuge is in a Bog, and in the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:50220:19"/>groſſeſt abſurdity; however I am of Opinion if ye ſearch your own Hearts, ye do not believe this, nor believe your ſelves bound to ſuch an Allegiance ſtill to King <hi>James</hi> as ye pretend, for if ye were, ye were bound to do all ye can to bring him in again, <hi>to defend him in all his Rights, Titles, Preheminencies, and Authorities,</hi> according to your Oath of Allegiance to him if that ſtill oblige you, and to oppoſe all the Enemies to his juſt and rightful Claim and Authority, and to uſe ſome other Weapons for him than thoſe of Prayers and Tears, and to live no longer peaceably under this Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment than ye have a power and opportunity to deſtroy it; and yet I dare ſay the beſt and moſt conſcientious among you are not of this Mind, ſo that if you will give me leave to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt the ſame favor of you, which you have done of me <hi>to return ſuch a ſerious</hi> and ſincere <hi>anſwer</hi> to theſe Queries as <hi>you will not be aſhamed of at the laſt day,</hi> you will find you are more apt to contradict your ſelves and your own Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples in ſeveral things then any of us are in the buſineſs of <hi>Non-Reſiſtance</hi> and <hi>Paſſive Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly, I would ſeriouſly ask you one Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:50220:20"/>more: <hi>Whether if it be lawful to take the Oathes, and come in to the Government, it be not a</hi> Sin <hi>to refuſe them, and ſtand out?</hi> This I ask be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I am apt to believe that moſt of you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider only the loſs of your Preferments, and Worldly Intereſts as the only danger and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard on one ſide, whereas there is a ſin and all the Conſequencies of <hi>that</hi> on the other; and therefore ye look upon it as much ſafer and bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to venture the penalty than the crime. Now if this were all, I confeſs it is ſo to a very good man who has lively Thoughts of Religion upon his Mind, and near Thoughts of Death, and mean Thoughts of this World, as a Wiſe Man cannot but have, who has lived long in it and enjoyed it, and even a Man of no great Goodneſs may be eaſily brought to do this when the Worldly loſs and danger is not ſo certain but he has hopes by many ways to E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape it, and eſpecially at a time when 'tis ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry uncertain which ſide is like to be the looſer or the Gainer as to this World. But This is by no means putting the caſe right, nor uſing a juſt Ballance to weigh the difficulties on both ſides, but 'tis leaving out the heavieſt weight on one ſide which ſhould turn the ſcale againſt all the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:50220:20"/>reſt, Worldly Intereſt alone is eaſily weighed down with Peace of Mind, and a mans Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Intereſt, and ſometimes with the mere Glory and Opinion of Suffering Perſecution for Conſcience ſake, and the enjoying and gratify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a ſtiff and obſtinate Humour that is not humble enough to yield or to retract a miſtake; but the Conſideration of that Miſchief which a man does to Religion, to the Church whoſe Service he deſerts, to the Kingdom whoſe Peace he diſturbs, to his Pariſh and Flock whom he forſakes, to his Family, whom he ruins and undoes, and how much he becomes an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument, though againſt his Will, to ſerve <hi>Popery</hi> and the worſt Intereſt i'the World, this ſhould open his eyes and make him ſee a greater danger and evil on the other ſide then the mere loſs of his Worldly Intereſt, and that it muſt be one of the greateſt ſins that can be and the moſt big with evil Conſequences to ſtand out, if it be not utterly ſinful and unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in it ſelf to come in, and therefore if any man does the former out of any humour, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſeneſs or revenge becauſe he is not pleaſed or things are not carried to his Mind, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he will not be thought to Change his
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:50220:21"/>Opinion, or ſneakingly come in to ſave his Preferment, and be laughed at for ſo doing, if it be from a point of Honour or any other reaſon but a Point of Conſcience, ſuch an one commits a greater Sin than can be committed on the other ſide, and runs the Hazard of loſing ſomthing greater than the beſt Dignity and Promotion in this World. This I would therefore have ye all ſeriouſly conſider and anſwer it, if not to me, yet to God and your own Conſciences. Farewel, and remember you were the Aggreſſor.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:50220:21"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
